برج عبدالو، قرية سورية من أقدم القرى التي استوطنها الإنسان
في منطقة عفرين، وهي تقع على السفح الغربي الشمالي لجبل ليلون.
Burj Abdalo, a Syrian village, is one of the oldest villages
settled by humans in the Afrin region. It is located on the
northwestern slope of Mount Laylun.
يحدها نهر عفرين من الشمال ويمكن الوصول إليها من طريقين
أساسيين:
It is bordered by the Afrin River to the north, and can be
reached via two main routes:
الطريق الأول عفرين الباسوطة الغزاوية والطريق الثاني حلب دارة
عزة الغزاوية ثم برج عبدالو.
the first is Afrin - Al-Basouta - Al-Ghazawiya, and the
second is Aleppo - Darat Izza - Al-Ghazawiya, then Burj
Abdalo.
جولتنا لهالأسبوع رح تكون من برج عبدالو. تابعونا.
Our tour this week will be from Burj Abdalo. Stay tuned.
قرية برج عبدالو. تقع قرية برج عبدالو أو برج عبد الله كما هو
اسمها رسميا على السفح الغربي لجبل ليلون جنوب مدينة عفرين
بنحو 12 كيلومترا.
Burj Abdalo village. Burj Abdalo village, or Burj Abdullah
as it is officially named, is located on the western slope
of Mount Laylun, about 12 kilometers south of the city of
Afrin.
وهي قرية سياحية تشتهر ببحيرة السد التي أنشئت على نهر عفرين
والذي يمر شمال القرية،
It is a tourist village famous for the dam lake that was
built on the Afrin River, which passes north of the village,
وأيضا كانت تشتهر بالمطاعم السياحية والغابات الموجودة قرب
البحيرة.
and it was also famous for the tourist restaurants and
forests located near the lake.
سكان القرية بالأصل حوالي 400 عائلة يعمل معظمهم بالزراعات
المروية
The village originally had about 400 families, most of whom
work in irrigated agriculture,
وخاصة زراعة الرمان والتفاح والسفرجل والإجاص، وزراعة الزيتون
البعلية إضافة للخضراوات ولبعض المحاصيل الزراعية كالقمح.
especially growing pomegranates, apples, quinces, and pears,
as well as rain-fed olive farming, in addition to vegetables
and some agricultural crops like wheat.
نزح إليها العديد من العائلات السورية من مناطق مختلفة يعمل
معظمهم كيد عاملة في بساتين القرية.
Many Syrian families from different regions have been
displaced there, most of whom work as laborers in the
village's orchards.
وبرج عبدالو قرية قديمة جدا، حيث عثرت البعثة الأثرية
اليابانية في عام 1993 في كهف الدودرية الواقع في تلة موسى
جنوب القرية على هيكل عظمي كامل لطفل،
Burj Abdalo is a very old village, as the Japanese
archaeological mission found a complete skeleton of a child
in 1993 in the Dederiyeh Cave, located in Talat Musa south
of the village,
وقدر علماء البعثة عمر العظام بـ 100 ألف سنة.
and the mission's scientists estimated the age of the bones
to be 100,000 years.
كما يوجد في وسط القرية أبنية حديثة بنيت من بقايا برج عبدالو
الروماني القديم، والذي أخذت القرية اسمها منه،
There are also modern buildings in the center of the village
built from the remains of the old Roman tower of Abdalo,
from which the village took its name.
وهو جزء من شبكة أبراج بناها الرومان في المنطقة لمراقبة الطرق
العسكرية والتجارية.
It is part of a network of towers built by the Romans in the
area to monitor military and trade routes.
يتميز المجتمع في قرية برج عبدالو بالطبيعة الفلاحية الزراعية،
The society in Burj Abdalo village is characterized by its
agricultural, peasant nature,
نظرا لانتشار الزراعة المروية فيها بسبب مرور نهر عفرين شمالي
القرية ووجود سد تسقى منه الأراضي الزراعية.
due to the prevalence of irrigated farming, the passage of
the Afrin River north of the village, and the existence of a
dam from which the agricultural lands are irrigated.
ويعمل معظم النازحون في الأراضي الزراعية كعمال.
Most displaced people work in the agricultural lands as
laborers.
يتميز أهالي برج عبدالو بالطبيعة المتسامحة والمنفتحة على
الآخرين.
The people of Burj Abdalo are known for their tolerant and
open nature towards others.
سنكون معكم في هذه الفقرة في جولة في حارات وأزقة برج عبدالو.
تابعونا.
We will be with you in this segment on a tour of the
neighborhoods and alleys of Burj Abdalo. Stay tuned.
السلام عليكم.
Peace be upon you.
أهلا وسهلا.
Welcome.
يعطيك العافية.
May God give you health.
الله يعافيك.
May God give you health too.
حضرتك من هون؟
Are you from here?
لا والله، من ريف حلب الجنوبي.
No, by God, from the southern countryside of Aleppo.
أهلا وسهلا فيكي. قد إيش صار لك هون؟
Welcome. How long have you been here?
والله شي حوالي سنتين.
By God, about two years.
سنتين، إيش وضع الناس هون؟ النازحين؟ كيف عايشين؟
Two years. How are the people doing here? The displaced? How
are they living?
والله أمورهم بسيطة جدا.
By God, their situation is very simple.
كيف؟
How so?
لا لهم معين لا لهم شي.
They have no breadwinner, they have nothing.
طيب، أنت وين زوجك؟ وين أولادك؟ شو عندك أولاد؟
Okay, where is your husband? Where are your children? What
children do you have?
والله عندي صبي واحد وعندي بنتين.
By God, I have one boy and two girls.
معك هن؟
Are they with you?
لا، بس البنات معي.
No, only the girls are with me.
زوجك؟
Your husband?
زوجي عند أهله.
My husband is with his family.
ليش عند أهله؟
Why is he with his family?
إي، تركني يعني صار له 5-6 سنين عند أهله.
Yes, he left me, meaning he has been with his family for 5-6
years.
طيب، كيف عايشين لك أنتو؟
Okay, so how are you living?
والله عايشين أمورنا بسيطة يعني لا عنا شي لا عنا معين لا عنا
حدا.
By God, we are living a simple life, meaning we have
nothing, no provider, no one.
تشتغلي هون في الأرض مع الناس؟
Do you work here on the land with people?
لا والله.
No, by God.
لكا؟
So what do you do?
ما معي حدا أشتغل.
I don't have anyone to work with.
كيف لك عايشة؟
So how are you living?
والله عايشة على رب العالمين، إيش بدي أساوي؟ ما عنا حدا
يشتغل، أنا وبناتي.
By God, living by the grace of the Lord of the Worlds. What
should I do? We have no one to work, just me and my
daughters.
البيت الساكنينه أجار ولا كيف؟
The house you're living in, is it rented or what?
لا مو أجار، حرام مو أجار. بس ساكنين عند وحدة ختيارة.
No, it's not rent, poor thing, not rent. We are just staying
with an old woman.
يعني مبركتك عندها؟
You mean she is letting you stay with her?
إي، مبركتني عندها، إي.
Yes, she's letting me stay with her, yes.
الله يعطيك العافية.
May God give you health.
الله يعافيك.
May God give you health too.
السلام عليكم.
Peace be upon you.
يا أهلا وسهلا.
Welcome.
شلونكم؟ كيف أحوالكم؟
How are you? How are things?
الحمد لله. كيفكم أنتم؟ الله يعافيك.
Thank God. How are you? May God give you health.
من وين حضرتك؟
Where are you from?
أنا من ريف حلب الجنوبي.
I am from the southern countryside of Aleppo.
يا أهلا وسهلا.
Welcome.
أهلا فيك.
Welcome to you too.
جاي أسأل، يعني عن وضع الناس هون، شلون وضع الناس؟
I came to ask, I mean, about the situation of the people
here. How is the people's situation?
صعب، صعب.
Difficult, difficult.
شلون صعب؟ يعني احكي لي شلون صعب؟
How is it difficult? Tell me how it is difficult.
أخي هلق كل شي غالي، الدولار غالي وكل شي عم ينباع على
الدولار.
Brother, now everything is expensive. The dollar is
expensive and everything is being sold in dollars.
حتى المازوت والمي وصهاريج المي والخبز وشغلات كل شي وخضار
وفواكه كل شي،
Even fuel oil, water, water tanks, bread, things,
everything, vegetables and fruits, everything.
وعندنا موسمنا رخيص. عنا أكتر شي الرمان يعني، رخيص عم ينباع،
And our season's harvest is cheap. We mostly have
pomegranates, they are being sold cheaply.
يعني الوضع حتى الوضع الزراعي تعبان يعني العالم تعبانة يعني.
I mean, the situation, even the agricultural situation is
poor, people are exhausted.
يعني يا دوب الواحد يعيش حاله بالزور يعني.
Okay.
It means one can barely survive, barely.
يا دوب، هلق أهل البرج بيشتغلوا بالزراعة، النازحين إيش
بيشتغلوا؟
Barely. Now, the people of the Burj work in agriculture.
What do the displaced work in?
عامل يومي.
Daily laborer.
عامل يومي، بيشتغلوا.
Daily laborers, that's how they work.
أهل البرج بيشتغلوا غير بالزراعة؟
Do the people of the Burj work in anything other than
agriculture?
يعني في غير الزراعة بيشتغلوا فيها أهل البرج؟
What do you mean?
I mean, is there anything other than agriculture that the
people of the Burj work in?
لا لا، أشجار أكتر شي.
No, no. Trees mostly.
أشجار أكتر شي.
Trees mostly.
أشجار، الرمان أكتر شي.
Trees, pomegranates mostly.
أنا شايف قدامي بطاطا، بندورة، تفاح، شو أسعارهم؟
I see potatoes, tomatoes, apples in front of me, what are
their prices?
البطاطا بـ 250، بندورة بـ 600، تفاح بـ 400. الخسة حقها 150
ليرة خسة يعني، كيلو الفجل 100 ليرة.
Potatoes are 250, tomatoes are 600, apples are 400. A
lettuce is 150 liras, just lettuce, a kilo of radishes is
100 liras.
ربطة الخبز؟
A bundle of bread?
300 ليرة.
300 liras.
300 ليرة. هون الناس على شو عم تدفى هلق بالشتاء؟
300 liras. What do people use for heating here now in
winter?
حطب.
Firewood.
حطب، المازوت غالي، برميل المازوت 140 ألف، 165 ألف. حطب،
بيجمعوا حطب بيشتروا...
Firewood. Fuel oil is expensive, a barrel of fuel oil is 140
thousand, 165 thousand. Firewood, they gather firewood, they
buy...
طن الحطب شقد؟ اللي ما بيشتروا، اللي بيجمعوا بيشتروا...
How much is a ton of firewood? Those who don't buy, who
gather... they buy...
لا بيشتروا، في ناس بيشتروا كمان.
No, they buy, there are people who buy as well.
شقد؟
How much?
الطن بـ 45 ألف.
A ton is 45 thousand.
45 ألف.
45 thousand.
إي.
Yes.
حسبنا الله ونعم الوكيل.
God is sufficient for us, and He is the best disposer of
affairs.
ضعيف... كل شي ضعيف.
Weak... everything is weak.
يعني العالم مدبرة حالها ديفش؟
So people are just barely scraping by?
ديفش، كأنه عايشين بالمخيم.
Scraping by, it's like living in a camp.
يلا الله يعين. الله يعطيك العافية.
May God help us all. May God give you health.
أهلا وسهلا، الله معك مع السلامة.
Welcome, God be with you, goodbye.
الله يسلمك.
May God keep you safe.
أهلا وسهلا.
Welcome.
المجتمع في برج عبدالو يتكون من مكونات ثلاث: العرب والكرد
المسلمين والإيزيديين.
The society in Burj Abdalo consists of three components:
Arabs, Muslim Kurds, and Yazidis.
في هذه الفقرة سنتكلم عن التراث والفلكلور الشعبي في برج
عبدالو وأيضا سنتكلم عن الإيزيديين وعاداتهم في هذه القرية.
تابعونا.
In this segment, we will talk about the heritage and popular
folklore in Burj Abdalo, and we will also talk about the
Yazidis and their customs in this village. Stay tuned.
السلام عليكم.
Peace be upon you.
وعليكم السلام ورحمة الله وبركاته.
Peace, mercy, and blessings of God be upon you.
الشيخ محمد هون؟
Is Sheikh Mohammad here?
أهلا ومرحبتين.
Welcome.
يا رب. شرف.
Oh Lord. Come in.
تفضل يا رب.
Please, come in.
السلام عليكم.
Peace be upon you.
وعليكم السلام أهلا وسهلا.
Peace be upon you, welcome.
الله يعطيكم العافية.
May God give you health.
الله يعافيك أهلا وسهلا.
May God give you health, welcome.
نتعرف عليكم؟
May we know your names?
عمر رشيد من أهالي برج عبدالو.
Omar Rasheed, from the people of Burj Abdalo.
أهلا وسهلا.
Welcome.
مصطفى عثمان علي من أهالي برج عبدالو.
Mustafa Othman Ali, from the people of Burj Abdalo.
أهلا وسهلا.
Welcome.
محمد خليل كالو، شيخ مرجعية الديانة اليزيدية في عفرين كانت،
والآن هون.
Mohammad Khalil Kalo, Sheikh of the religious authority for
the Yazidi religion in Afrin, and now here.
أهلا وسهلا.
Welcome.
الله يسلمك.
May God keep you safe.
نجيب من باصوطة.
Najeeb from Basouta.
أهلا وسهلا.
Welcome.
جبر المحمد من حماة.
Jaber Al-Mohammad from Hama.
أهلا وسهلا.
Welcome.
بدي أبدأ معك.
I want to start with you.
تفضل.
Please go ahead.
تحكي لنا شوي أنت والأستاذ عن موضوع الفلكلور والتراث الشعبي
اللي هون.
Tell us a bit, you and the teacher, about the folklore and
popular heritage here.
إيش اللي بيميز يعني برج عبدالو بعاداتها وتقاليدها وفلكلورها
عن باقي القرى اللي حواليها مثل الغزاوية مثل الباصوطة وغيره؟
What distinguishes Burj Abdalo, its customs, traditions, and
folklore, from the other surrounding villages like Al-
Ghazawiya, Basouta, and others?
كتراثنا برج عبدالو غزاوي كفرزيت باصوطة بتشبه بعضهم وعاداتنا
وتقاليدنا بنسبة تقريبا نحن صايرين على المركز.
As our heritage, Burj Abdalo, Ghazawiya, Kfarzeet, Basouta
are similar to each other, and our customs and traditions
are somewhat similar, we are almost central.
يعني كيف على المركز؟
What do you mean by central?
مركز عفرين.
The center of Afrin.
يعني كل الفلكلور والتراث والعادات والتقاليد متشابهة؟
So all the folklore, heritage, customs, and traditions are
similar?
كنسبة لمنطقة عفرين في هداك القرى بلكي ناحية بلبل جنديرس شران
بتختلف شوي، بس هون عادات تقاليد تراث فلكلور كلها مثل البعض.
Relative to the Afrin region, in those villages maybe
towards Bulbul, Jindires, Sharran, they differ a bit. But
here, customs, traditions, heritage, folklore are all the
same.
طيب بدي أنتقل للأستاذ بسألك يعني هلق إيش هي أهم أنواع
الدبكات وأهم يعني أنواع الأغاني اللي تغنى في برج عبدالو؟
Okay, I want to move to the teacher and ask you, what are
the most important types of Dabke and the most important
types of songs sung in Burj Abdalo?
يا سيدي الأغنيات تقريبا يعني في مشكل وملون. في عادي في مثلا
فلكلور عادي يعني ونحن هلق، نحن، أنا، أنا المطرب بغني.
Sir, the songs are almost, I mean, mixed and colorful. There
are regular ones, there's regular folklore, for example, and
we now, we, I, I am the singer, I sing.
أشهر الأغاني شو هي؟
What are the most famous songs?
مثلا عيشيبي، عيشة، حمو، ...
For example, Ayshebe, Aysha, Hamo...
هلق بدي أنتقل للشيخ محمد أسأله شوي إيش اللي بيميز العادات
والتقاليد اللي بتخص الإيزيديين، بعدين نرجع نسمع منكم شي.
Now I want to move to Sheikh Mohammad, to ask him a bit
about what distinguishes the customs and traditions of the
Yazidis, and then we'll come back to hear something from
you.
ماشي على راسي.
Sure, on my head.
شيخ محمد، سمعني، أنت شيخ مرجعية يعني الإيزيديين في عفرين ما
هيك؟
Sheikh Mohammad, listen to me. You are a Sheikh of the
religious authority, meaning of the Yazidis in Afrin, right?
نعم. نعم.
Yes, yes.
إيش اللي بيميز الإيزيديين عن الكرد المسلمين؟
What distinguishes the Yazidis from the Muslim Kurds?
عادات الاديان يعني بيختلف شوية. مثلا على صيام، نحن عنا ثلاث
أيام صيام عم نصوم.
The religious customs, I mean, differ a little. For example,
regarding fasting, we have three days of fasting that we
observe.
مثلا بيختلف وقت اللي بنلقن، عم نلقن الميت عم نلقن.
For example, it differs when we recite the Shahada (talqin),
we recite it to the deceased.
يعني تقريبا عاداتنا والمسلم والايزيدي كله يعني جنب بعض مثلا
عم ندفن الميت مثل بعض عم نلبسه مثل بعض يعني عم نسوي مثل بعض.
I mean, generally, our customs, and the Muslims and the
Yazidis, are all practically the same. For example, we bury
the dead the same way, we shroud them the same way, I mean
we do things the same way.
كل شيء مثل بعض بس شوي هيك بيختلف أوقات يعني من شيء هيك يعني.
Everything is the same, but it differs just a little bit at
times, I mean in certain things like that.
أعيادكم إيمت؟ إيمت بتعيدوا؟
When are your holidays? When do you celebrate?
عيدنا هلق برأس الكانون أول،
Our holiday now is at the beginning of December,
صمنا 3 أيام عيدنا،
We fasted for 3 days and celebrated,
وبـ 14 شباط في كمان عندنا عيد خضر الياس عم نقول،
And on February 14th we also have the holiday of Khidr
Elias, as we call it,
وفي 4 نيسان حساب شرقي،
And on April 4th, by the eastern calendar,
كمان هذا عندنا عيد الربيع.
we also have our Spring holiday.
خليني أرجع للشباب يسمعونا هيك يعني شيء أغنية من هون،
Let me go back to the guys to play us a song from here,
عيشانة، حمو، كذا، يعني بتميز هالبلدة وهالمنطقة،
Ayshana, Hamo, or something like that, which distinguishes
this town and this region,
برج عبدالو، الغزاوية، الباسوطة، شو بدكم تسمعونا؟
Burj Abdalo, Ghazawiya, Basouta, what are you going to play
for us?
خيو الطنبور والله صار له عشرين سنة ما عم بشتغل.
Brother, the tanbur hasn't been played for twenty years to
be honest.
Lê lê lê lê lê lê lê...
Oy oy Eyşanê lê lê lê lê oy oy...
Oh, oh, Ayshane, le le le le, oh, oh...
Ez bi qurbana teqla çavê reş û belek oy Eyşê mînanî çavê
çîko oy oy...
Let me be a sacrifice to your beautiful black and white
eyes, oh Ayshe, like the eyes of a bird, oh oh...
Bila eşîr ba ta şîn a tar serê çatan û rîta oy Eyşê li gundî
ko oy oy oy...
Let the tribe be up to the top of the mountains and plains,
oh Ayshe, in the village of... oh oh oh...
Bila her û xortî wekî ba şebavgiya bişitandin da Eyşana min
a li gundî koo...
Let the young men go like the wind blowing the grass for my
Ayshana in the village of...
Lê lê lê lê lê lê lê...
Oy oy çelenga min lê lê lê lê...
Oh oh my beautiful one, le le le le...
الله يعطيكم العافية.
May God give you health.
شو كان عم يحكي؟ شو كان عم يغني بالعربي؟
May God give you health too.
What was he saying? What was he singing in Arabic?
بالعربي عيشة.
In Arabic, Aysha.
إيه شو الأغنية عم تقول؟
Yes, what is the song saying?
يعني أغنية، بيقول، يعني سألك كثير بيحبوا العيشة، هذا اللي
بيغني عليه،
I mean the song says, like you asked they love Aysha a lot,
this is what he's singing about,
يعني بيقول، إجى العزرائيل مثلاً، الليلة اللي بده يتجوزوا بها
معناه،
Meaning it says, Azrael came for example, on the night they
were supposed to get married,
إجى العزرائيل بده يقبض روح البنت.
Azrael came to take the girl's soul.
يعني إيش قد بيدخل بيدخل عزرائيل بيقول،
I mean no matter how much he intervenes, Azrael says,
ما معي أمر لأوصلكم أخليكم تتجوزوا مثلاً.
I don't have orders to let you reach each other and let you
get married, for example.
ما بنعرف بالعربي نجاوبك!
We don't know how to answer you in Arabic!
الله يعطيكم العافية. شكراً لكم.
May God give you health. Thank you.
أهلاً وسهلاً حياك الله.
Welcome, may God greet you.
قرية برج عبدالو، وعلى الرغم من صغر حجمها، إلا أنها موغلة
جداً في القدم.
The village of Burj Abdalo, despite its small size, is very
deeply rooted in ancient times.
فقد وجد في الجهة الجنوبية من القرية، وبالتحديد في منطقة تلة
موسى التي يكثر فيها المغارات،
In the southern part of the village, specifically in the
area of Talat Musa, where caves are abundant,
وفي مغارة الديدرية بالتحديد، عثرت البعثة اليابانية السورية
في عام 1989
and in the Dederiyeh Cave specifically, the joint Syrian-
Japanese mission in 1989 found
على هيكل عظمي لطفل قدرت عمره بأكثر من 100 ألف عام.
a skeleton of a child estimated to be over 100,000 years
old.
أيضاً في القرية هناك برج روماني يعرف باسم برج عبدالو أو برج
عبد الله،
Also in the village, there is a Roman tower known as the
Tower of Abdalo or the Tower of Abdullah,
وقد سميت هذه القرية نسبة لهذا البرج.
and this village was named after this tower.
سنكون في هذا اللقاء عن تاريخ القرية مع مختار القرية،
In this interview about the village's history, we will be
with the village mukhtar,
الأستاذ كاميران مصطفى، ليحدثنا عن تاريخ قرية برج عبدالو،
تابعونا.
Mr. Kamiran Mustafa, to talk to us about the history of the
village of Burj Abdalo, stay with us.
يعطيك العافية مختار.
May God give you health, Mukhtar.
الله يعافيك يا هلا.
May God give you health, welcome.
هلق أنت حضرتك من أبناء قرية برج عبدالو، وحفظان تاريخها.
Now, you are one of the sons of the village of Burj Abdalo,
and you have memorized its history.
نعم.
Yes.
تحكي لنا نحن اليوم وين واقفين حالياً؟
Can you tell us where we are currently standing today?
يعني حالياً واقفين عند البرج.
Well, currently we are standing at the tower.
يعني البرج كان موجود محل ما نحن واقفين.
I mean, the tower was located right where we are standing.
نعم.
Yes.
بعد ما البرج... يعني كان برج روماني أساسه.
After the tower... I mean, it was originally a Roman tower.
إيه وانهدم البرج عمروه، يعني أخذوا هالحجار عمروه فيه بناء...
Yes, and the tower was destroyed and they built, meaning
they took these stones and built a building with them...
ويعني نسبة، اسم الضيعة نسبة إلى برج عبدالو نسبة إلى البرج
يعني،
And the name of the village is attributed to the Tower of
Abdalo, meaning attributed to the tower,
بيقولوا كان ساكن جنب البرج شخص اسمه عبدالو.
they say a person named Abdalo used to live next to the
tower.
نعم.
Yes.
ونسبة إلى هالشخص سميت برج عبدالو.
And attributed to this person, it was named Burj Abdalo.
طيب، هلق القرية فيها برج اسمه برج عبدالو أو برج عبد الله،
وسميت بهذا الاسم بسبب هذا البرج.
Okay, now the village has a tower named Burj Abdalo or Burj
Abdullah, and it was named this because of this tower.
البرج في كمان أيضاً حول قرية البرج في عدة أبراج أخرى،
As for the tower, there are also several other towers around
the village of the tower,
شو كان وظيفة هيدا البرج وهي الأبراج الموجودة هون؟
what was the function of this tower and these towers located
here?
وظيفة هالبرج كان في طريق حرير، هالبرج كان مثل برج يعني مثل
مراسلة.
The function of this tower was on the Silk Road, this tower
was like a tower for correspondence.
يعني بريد، يعني يصير مثل بريد يبعثوا رسائل لبعض مثلاً.
Like a post, I mean it acted like a post to send messages to
each other for example.
هيك كان يعني وظيفته الأساسية يعني.
This was its main function.
حماية القوافل، يعني قوافل عسكرية وتجارية الرومانية؟
Protecting convoys, meaning Roman military and commercial
convoys?
نعم، يعني كان اختصاص البرج يعني كان أولي زمان يقولوا طريق
الحرير.
Yes, I mean the tower's specialty was, in the old times they
used to say the Silk Road.
طريق الحرير يعني يأمنوا القوافل.
The Silk Road, meaning they secure the convoys.
تمام؟ يعني بهالشكل كان يعني سمي بالبرج.
Right? So in this way it was named the tower.
والضيعة سميت على اسمه.
And the village was named after it.
طيب، أحجار، أحجار البرج وين صارت؟
Okay, the stones, where did the stones of the tower go?
صارت عمروا فيها هون بناء.
They were used to build a building here.
وينه؟ خلينا نقرب لقدام شوي.
Where is it? Let's get a bit closer.
هذا البناء هون وراء، قفانا يعني.
This building here behind, behind us I mean.
هذا البناء، شو هذا البناء؟
This building, what is this building?
بناء سكن يعني.
A residential building.
مين اللي عمره وايمتى؟
Who built it and when?
عمروه هذول... شيخ عمر كيالي.
It was built by... Sheikh Omar Kayali.
نعم.
Yes.
خلينا هلق نحكي عن مغارة الديدرية، اللي هي صايرة في تلة موسى،
Let's talk now about the Dederiyeh Cave, which is located in
Talat Musa,
تلة موسى أو تلة موس، اللي صايرة قبلي الضيعة أو جنوب الضيعة.
Talat Musa or Talat Mous, which is located south of the
village.
فينا نوصل لها؟
Can we reach it?
إي والله حالياً بسبب الأمطار وال... يعني السير عالمغارة وعلى
التلة موس صعبة بهالوقت يعني.
Yes, but honestly currently due to the rain and... I mean
walking to the cave and Talat Mous is difficult at this
time.
طيب احكي لي عنها.
Alright, tell me about it.
تلة موس يعني هي مؤلفة تلة، مؤلفة لعدة مغر، مغر.
Talat Mous is made up of a hill, consisting of several
caves, caves.
في مغر، يعني تنزل محفور بالحجر جوا، محفور بحجر،
There are caves, meaning you go down and it's carved into
the stone inside, carved in stone,
مثل مثلاً غرفة هون، غرفة بالوجه، وغرفة... يعني ثلاث غرف.
like for example a room here, a room in front, and a room...
meaning three rooms.
وفي حجرة كبيرة يعني طولها يعني شي بـ 5 أمتار بـ 4، حجرة فرش،
خفي.
And there's a large stone room, its length is about 5 meters
by 4, a paved room, hidden.
وفي عليها علامات، أولي مثلاً يلعبوا مثل ضامة، شغلة هيك،
هالأمور...
And there are marks on it, in the old days for example they
used to play things like checkers, things like that, these
things...
أنا أقصد إنه يعني بهذه المغارات سكن الإنسان الأول في
هالمنطقة.
I mean that in these caves the early humans lived in this
region.
نعم.
Yes.
استوطن الإنسان الأول هون.
Early humans settled here.
تمام.
Exactly.
ومن ثم انتقل السكن من تلة موس إلى شمالي القرية.
And then the settlement moved from Talat Mous to the north
of the village.
قشلة، فوق الضيعة اسمها قشلة.
Qishla, above the village, it's called Qishla.
البيوت انتقلت من هنيك إلى قشلة.
The houses moved from there to Qishla.
ولحد الآن في آثار للعمار، يعني خرابات وهالأمور يعني موجودة
لحد الآن.
And until now there are ruins of buildings, meaning ruins
and these things are still present until now.
في إمكاننا نشوفها؟
Can we see them?
إي نعم.
Yes, indeed.
معناها رح نروح الآن على منطقة القشلة اللي عم تسميها أنت،
This means we will go now to the Qishla area that you are
calling it,
منطقة الخراب اللي انتقل فيها الإنسان بالسكن من تلة موس إلى
الشمال، وبعدين رح نروح لوين؟
the ruined area where humans moved their settlement from
Talat Mous to the north, and then where will we go?
عالسد، هذا السد سياحي، وخدمي يعني،
To the dam, this is a tourist and service dam, I mean,
يعني سد لاستخدام لروي الأراضي الزراعية، كمعلم سياحي.
it's a dam used for irrigating agricultural lands, as a
tourist attraction.
لكنه هو معلم سياحي؟
But it is a tourist attraction?
فهو معلم سياحي، يعني منطقة سياحية.
It is a tourist attraction, meaning a tourist area.
طيب تفضل معنا.
Alright, please come with us.
مختار هلق نحن وصلنا لتلة القشلة، اللي هي الخراب،
Mukhtar, now we have arrived at the Qishla hill, which is
the ruins,
اللي انتقل الإنسان القديم من تلة موس لهون.
where the ancient human moved from Talat Mous to here.
لهون.
To here.
احكي لي عنها.
Tell me about it.
قبل 200 سنة، فوق هون بهالمنطقة،
200 years ago, up here in this area,
يعني في لحد الآن آثار للبيوت اللي كانوا معمرين مثلاً.
I mean there are still traces of the houses they built for
example.
بعد منه العالم نزلت من تلة القشلة لمكان الضيعة الحالية.
After that, the people came down from the Qishla hill to the
location of the current village.
محل البرج.
At the location of the tower.
إيه، يعني بهالفترة، يعني فترة النزلة من هون لتحت الضيعة يعني
في شي 250 سنة.
Yes, meaning in this period, the period of coming down from
here to below the village is about 250 years.
طيب هلق أنا هون شايف كأنه في كهوف، في شيء، في خرابات هيك
مبينة من هون شوي.
Okay, now I see here that there are caves, there are things,
there are some ruins visible from here a bit.
نعم نعم، في، في كهوف.
Yes, yes, there are, there are caves.
في فوق يعني محل ما أولي كانوا يخزنوا حب وما حب، يعني المونة،
There are up there, meaning where they used to store grain
and things, meaning the pantry,
خزانات صخرية كانوا موجودين، بالفوق على التلة القشلة هون
موجودين.
rocky tanks were present, up on the Qishla hill here they
are present.
هلا البعثة اليابانية السورية اللي نقبت في مغارة الديدرية...
Now the Syrian-Japanese mission that excavated in the
Dederiyeh Cave...
إيه.
Yes.
إيه، لقوا فيها طفل.
Yes, they found a child in it.
هيكل عظمي لطفل.
A skeleton of a child.
إي أي المنطقة هنيك، تلة موس ومغارة الديدرية...
Yes, that area there, Talat Mous and the Dederiyeh Cave...
هذول يعني المغارة قديماً العالم كان ساكنة فيها.
These, I mean the cave, in ancient times people used to live
in it.
معروف، عمر الهيكل العظمي للطفل قديش؟
Is it known, how old the skeleton of the child is?
والله هي...
Honestly it's...
قرأت إنه شي 100 ألف سنة.
I read that it's around 100,000 years.
إيه بلكي فوق كمان، يعني قديم جداً جداً يعني،
Yes, maybe even more, meaning very, very old,
هم اللي البعثة هي اللي فحصته وإنه...
they are the mission that examined it and that...
عمره...
its age...
English Translation
فوق ال 100 ألف سنة.
Over 100,000 years.
English Translation
فوق 100 ألف سنة.
Over 100,000 years.
English Translation
لذلك اعتبرت إنه هاد الموقع من أهم المواقع الأثرية السورية
وربما في العالم أجمع.
English Translation
Therefore, this site is considered one of the most important
archaeological sites in Syria, and perhaps in the whole
world.
English Translation
في العالم أجمع مزبوط، هنن قرروا هيك البعثة.
In the whole world, exactly. The expedition decided this.
English Translation
إنه فعلا هالمنطقة كانت قديما يعني.. يعني وجدوا هالطفل فيه
That truly this region was anciently... I mean, they found
this child in it.
English Translation
يعني قارنوا عمره ب 100 ألف سنة.
I mean, they estimated its age at 100,000 years.
English Translation
تمام، الآن رح نروح معك للسد.
Alright, now we will go with you to the dam.
English Translation
نعم.
Yes.
English Translation
الله يعطيك العافية.
May God give you health.
English Translation
الله يعافيك.
May God give you health too.
English Translation
مختار هلق نحن صرنا على السد.
Mukhtar, now we are at the dam.
English Translation
احكيلي عن هالسد شوي.
Tell me a bit about this dam.
English Translation
هذا السد، سد تجميعي.
This dam is a collection dam.
English Translation
تجميعي لزراعة.. لخدمة الأراضي الزراعية.
A collection dam for agriculture... to serve the
agricultural lands.
English Translation
يعني في خطين عنا، خط الراحة وفي خط..
I mean, we have two lines, the gravity line and there is a
line...
English Translation
بتطلع المي عليه بالمضخة يعني، بالمضخة بتطلع المي عليه.
The water goes up to it by a pump, I mean, the water goes up
to it by a pump.
English Translation
شي بيروح ع جنديرس وشي بيروح ع الغزاوية.
Some goes to Jindires and some goes to Ghazawiyah.
English Translation
إي ع الغزاوية وبرج عبدالو.
Yes, to Ghazawiyah and Burj Abdalo.
English Translation
طيب هلق هاد هو هون، هي الخزان هون هاد السد؟
Alright, now this is it here, this reservoir here, this dam?
English Translation
هاد خزان، جسم السد هون.
This is a reservoir, the body of the dam is here.
English Translation
من وين المي بتيجي هي؟
Where does this water come from?
English Translation
هي بتيجي من ميدانكي.
It comes from Midanki.
English Translation
نهر عفرين.
Afrin River.
English Translation
نهر عفرين إي.
Afrin River, yes.
English Translation
بتتجمع هون.
It collects here.
English Translation
تجميع هون إي.
Collection here, yes.
English Translation
الان ليش ما في مي؟
Now, why is there no water?
English Translation
حاليا بالشتي بيفتحوه مشان تعزيل، مع تعزيل السواقي وكذا
بهالأمور يعني.
English Translation
Currently, in the winter, they open it for clearing, along
with clearing the streams and such matters.
English Translation
طيب، هلق خلينا نمشي شوي.
Alright, now let's walk a bit.
English Translation
هاد هو النهر؟
This is the river?
English Translation
نعم، هاد النهر.
Yes, this is the river.
English Translation
مجرى النهر هون، كمان هو ماشي من هون؟
The course of the river is here, is it also flowing from
here?
English Translation
ماشي.. إي إله بوابة.
Flowing... yes, it has a gate.
English Translation
مجرى إله بوابة، بالشتي بيشيلوه مشان ما يطوف أو يتمدد.
The course has a gate, in the winter they remove it so it
doesn't flood or expand.
English Translation
بيفتحوه، بيشيلوا البوابة، البوابة هنيك بالشو اسمه بيشيلوها
بالهي.
English Translation
They open it, they remove the gate, the gate is over there
in the... they remove it with the thing.
English Translation
بيرفعوا البوابة، بيمشي بمجراه الطبيعي.
They raise the gate, it flows in its natural course.
English Translation
هلق هاد قلتلي بيروح هاد النهر رايح ع جنديرس فرعين.
Now this, you told me it goes, this river is going to
Jindires in two branches.
English Translation
وفرع بيروح ع الغزاوية وشي..
And a branch goes to Ghazawiyah and some...
English Translation
ع الغزاوية، السد إله يعني قسم، اسمه خط الراحة.
To Ghazawiyah, the dam has a section, called the gravity
line.
English Translation
هاد بدون مضخة بدون شي، بالراحة بتطلع من هون.. ع جنديرس.
This is without a pump, without anything, by gravity it goes
out from here... to Jindires.
English Translation
بتروي هالأراضي.
It irrigates these lands.
English Translation
طيب هلق الان أنا شايف هون خلفي شو هاد؟ هالمبنى شو هاد؟
Alright, now I see here behind me, what is this? This
building, what is this?
English Translation
هاد مطعم.
This is a restaurant.
English Translation
مطعم هاد.
A restaurant.
English Translation
مقصف، يعني منتزه.
A cafe, I mean a park.
English Translation
وهاد؟
And this?
English Translation
سياحي، نفسه كمان.
Touristic, the same as well.
English Translation
مطعم برج ومطعم لافينيا.
Burj Restaurant and Lavinia Restaurant.
English Translation
على أطراف السد.
On the edges of the dam.
English Translation
ونحن واقفين فوق الجسر؟
And we are standing on the bridge?
English Translation
نحن حاليا على جسم السد.. ع الجسر.
We are currently on the body of the dam... on the bridge.
English Translation
ع الجسر، ع جسم السد يعني واقفين.
On the bridge, on the body of the dam, I mean, we are
standing.
English Translation
اللي صاير يعني شمال طريق الغزاوية، باصوطة.
Which is located, I mean, north of the Ghazawiyah - Basouta
road.
English Translation
باصوطة نعم.
Basouta, yes.
English Translation
وهي غابات.
And these are forests.
English Translation
وهذا جبل ليلون.
And this is Mount Lelun.
English Translation
جبل ليلون.
Mount Lelun.
English Translation
ممدود من باصوطة يعني لدارة عزة.. لقلعة سمعان.
Extending from Basouta, I mean, to Darat Izza... to the
Citadel of Simeon.
English Translation
من باصوطة لدارة عزة، جبل سمعان، قلعة سمعان.
From Basouta to Darat Izza, Mount Simeon, the Citadel of
Simeon.
English Translation
إي، قلعة سمعان.
Yes, the Citadel of Simeon.
English Translation
الله يعطيك العافية.
May God give you health.
English Translation
أهلا وسهلا، وبسلامة، أهلين سلامات.
You're welcome, go in peace, welcome, greetings.
English Translation
انتهت رحلتنا معكم في قرية برج عبدالو في ريف عفرين الجنوبي.
Our journey with you in the village of Burj Abdalo in the
southern countryside of Afrin has ended.
English Translation
سنسافر معا في الأسابيع القادمة إلى مناطق سورية أخرى حبيبة.
We will travel together in the coming weeks to other beloved
Syrian regions.
English Translation
لمتابعة برنامجنا تابعوا صفحة الفيس الخاصة بالقناة.
To follow our program, follow the channel's Facebook page.
English Translation
وأيضا موقعنا على الانترنت
And also our website on the internet,
English Translation
halabtodaytv.net
السلام عليكم ورحمة الله وبركاته.
English Translation
Peace, mercy, and blessings of God be upon you.